Alright, so we are now in the eighth פרק perek and the
final section of בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, which is about death and
inheritance and wills. Very interesting whole rabbinic category of wills, which we'll
get to. I appreciate Dan Margulies filling in for me and beginning
this פרק. perek. I understand he gave a nice introduction.
And this פרק perek is very much a focus on the פסוקים
pesukim in the תורה, Torah, but also the question about how חזל
Chazal read those
פסוקים pesukim and sort of used their own logic in certain ways.
So what would the גמרא Gemara open, I mean the משנה Mishnah
opened with different types of relationships. Sometimes that you both inherit and
bequeath. By the way, that's the word for מנחילין. manchilin. Important to
know the right English terms.
For example, when somebody says are you מוציא motzi somebody their obligation
in קידוש, kiddush, the word is not do you fulfill,
that's the person who fulfills, it's do you discharge somebody's obligation. Dispense,
I like discharge is better. Anyway. Okay, people who inherit and bequeath,
and sometimes it only goes in one direction and sometimes it doesn't
go at all.
And the גמרא Gemara now is focused initially
on that the opening line in the משנה Mishnah is that a
father both inherits and bequeaths. And the גמרא Gemara says that's a
very tragic way of opening the משנה Mishnah for a father to
inherit from his son means that his son predeceased him, God forbid.
And that's a real tragedy. So why do we open that way?
So the גמרא Gemara says, well, because that's a חידוש. chiddush. And
that's not explicit in the פסוקים, pesukim, which is true. The פסוקים
pesukim only mention a son, a brother, an uncle. They don't mention
the case of the father. So now we have to figure out
both the principle of how do you know that a father can
inherit and how do you know where he appears in the line
of inheritance. Now, I want to sort of introduce something that maybe
it's a little early to introduce it, maybe not. Okay, but first
let's look at the פסוקים pesukim here. Okay.
And the פסוקים pesukim say, thank you Michael. The פסוקים pesukim say
as follows, במדבר כז. Bamidbar chaf-zayin. By the way, we only have
this פרשה parsha in the תורה Torah thanks to בנות צלפחד. benot
Tzelofchad. So here's an entire פרק perek that is due to the
self-advocacy of the women of בנות צלפחד. benot Tzelofchad. Not only does
that lead to them saying that daughters can inherit, but also for
the תורה Torah to explicate what the laws of inheritance are. Okay,
so here's what it says in פרק כז, perek chaf-zayin, פסוק ו,
pasuk vav, ויאמר ה' אל משה לאמר כן בנות צלפחד דברת נתן
תתן להם אחזת נחלה בתוך אחי אביהם והעברת את נחלת אביהן
להן. Vayomer Hashem el Moshe lemor, kein benot Tzelofchad dovrot, naton titen
lahem achuzat nachala betoch achei avihem ve'avarta et nachalat avihen lahen. I
want to say something which we're going to get to later today,
but I'm going to jump the gun and say it right now,
that the word והעברת, ve'avarta, you shall transfer, as opposed to ונתתם,
unetatem, you shall give the inheritance, רבי Rebbi is going to make
a דרשה drasha which I think is פשט pshat in the פסוקים,
pesukim, that he says the reason it uses the word to transfer
in the context of daughters is because the inheritance will eventually leave
the tribe. That normally things obviously pass from father to son or
to male relative, and a male relative in a patriarchy is a
member of the same tribe. Okay, but if you give it to
a daughter and the daughter marries a member of a different tribe,
as we know became the issue later in במדבר, Bamidbar, that they
said they're going to marry other men and the inheritance will leave
the tribe and so on. So then when they die, their husbands
or their male children who will be members of the other tribe
will inherit from them. So therefore when the inheritance, the land is
given to the daughters, it is eventually going to be passed away
from the tribe. And you could have like the tribe of, you
know, דן Dan here that has a little pocket here of שמעון
Shimon and a little pocket here of יהודה Yehuda and a little
pocket here of
אפרים Efrayim because the daughters inherited and then married others. So that's
why when it speaks about daughters twice the תורה Torah uses the
word והעברת. ve'avarta. Okay, one minute. So it
says והעברת את נחלת אביהן להן. ve'avarta et nachalat avihen lahen. ואל
בני ישראל תדבר לאמר איש כי ימות ובן אין לו והעברתם את
נחלתו לבתו. Ve'el benei Yisrael tedaber lemor, ish ki yamut uven ein
lo, ve'ahavartem et nachalato levito. You transfer it over to the daughter.
Okay, so obviously implies here's a man, he dies. Okay, the number
one is the sons. Okay, if there's no sons, daughters do not
inherit when there is sons. Then number two is daughters.
והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. ve'ahavartem et nachalato levito. And there it says
והעברתם. ve'ahavartem.
Okay. ואם אין לו בת ונתתם, Ve'im ein lo bat unetatem, now
it doesn't say והעברתם, ve'ahavartem, when it's talking about going to men
it says and you shall give it, ונתתם את נחלתו לאחיו. unetatem
et nachalato le'achiv. So if there's no sons and no daughters, number
three is brothers. Okay. We're going according to the פשט pshat right
now. Okay.
לאחיו. Le'achiv. ואם אין לו אחים ונתתם את נחלתו. Ve'im ein lo
achim unetatem et nachalato. to לאחי אביו. le-achei aviv. Okay, so here's
his father, okay, and here's his father's brother, uncle,
brother or father's brother, right?
Paternal.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Everything is relationships through the father because we're all
in a patriarchy. Okay.
Yeah, it's, it's, you know, so number three, number four is this
is in the פסוקים psukim to his uncle. Okay. ואם
אין אחים לאביו ונתתם את נחלתו לשארו הקרוב אליו ממשפחתו וירש אותה.
ve-im ein achim le-aviv u-netattem et nachalato li-she'ero ha-karov elav mi-mishpachto ve-yarash
otah. Then you shall give it to his closest שאר, she'er, שאר
she'er means his flesh, his closest flesh relative. Again, it doesn't explicitly
mention related through the father. The גמרא Gemara is going to get
to that, that it's a patriarchy and therefore the family relationships that
matter are through the father. Okay, so what you do not have
here is the case of this guy. Does the father ever inherit
and when does he inherit? And that's what we're going to be
figuring out with תוספות. Tosafot. Number one, how do you know the
father inherits?
So the גמרא Gemara says we know the father inherits because it
says לשארו, li-she'ero, שארו זו
אביו, she'ero zo aviv, you know, because כי שאר אביך הוא, ki
she'er avicha hu, כי שאר אביך הוא. ki she'er avicha hu. So
שארו she'ero we're going to say means father. And הקרוב אליו, ha-karov
elav, so now because it says הקרוב אליו, ha-karov elav, which says
the closer relative comes first, that's going to be very important. Because
חז"ל Chazal are going to say although that פסוק pasuk appears at
the end and it seems that this order is quite clear, because
it says that the basic rule is that the closer the relationship
the earlier on you come in the line of inheritance, that is
going to give us license and that's what's going to be a
lot of what today's דף daf is, to determine who is really
closer related and maybe the, and maybe it's not the way it
sounds in the פסוקים. psukim. So first of all, if we were
to just ask, clearly the father should come before whom in this
order, one, two, three, four, if we had to insert the father?
The uncles. Right, clearly the father should come before the uncles, because
the father's brother is more distant to the guy who dies than
the father, right? So if we're going to insert the father with
the principle of the closer the relationship the earlier you are in
inheritance, there's no question we would put the father at four and
the father's brother at five. But the גמרא Gemara is not satisfied
with that. And the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the
father is even a closer relationship and it's going to insert him
not just before the father's brother, but it's going to insert him
here, before the brother. First you go to children and if no
children then father, and if no father then you go to brother.
So that's what the focus of the גמרא Gemara today is going
to be, not only to assert that the father gets it and
to assert that there is a, a hierarchy based on degree of
relationship, but also that we are not just going to insert the
father in the obvious slot, but understand against the פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim that the father is a closer relationship than the
brother, insert the father here. I'll take questions one minute, I just
want to tell you one thing, which is the principle we're going
to get to and it might be early to say it. If
it's too complicated ignore it, but it's an important principle. And that's
the idea of, although all the גמרא Gemara we're learning with is
just a list, here are the list of closest relatives: first son,
then daughter, then father, then brother, then uncle, then this, then this,
then it's just a straight list to read. A logic that the
גמרא Gemara says once we put the father before the brother, that's
where we're going to wind up, the father's going to be, you
know, two, let's say, you know, 3A and the brother's going to
be 3B, once we put the father before the brother the logic
is going to work as follows. Okay, all you really have to
know to know relatives is the order of first children, then father.
Why? Because here's how it works. If there's children, obviously sons come
before daughters. If there's no children, then father. If there's no father,
you don't, you don't need any of this rest. You don't need
to tell me brother and father's brother based on the following mechanism.
It's called מישמש mishmesh machine and יורש בקבר. yoresh be-kever. Okay, if
there's no father you imagine it as if the father inherited and
then the father died. So if the father inherited and then died,
who would get it? The children, the brothers. By the way, if
there are no brothers, you know who gets before the father's brother?
Sisters. Because it's as if the father inherited and died and therefore
it would go to first brother then sisters. Now if there are
no brothers or sisters, so if there are no brothers or sisters
to this guy who does it go to? If somebody died and
he has, I mean if he has no sons or daughters, who
would it go to? It would go to his father, right? But
his father is dead so it would go to his father's children
which is his, the brother. And if there's no... Father's brothers but
there's sisters, it would go, the aunt, it would go to the
aunt. By the way, the same is true, let's say there are
no sons, but the son has a child, a surviving child. It
goes to the surviving child. So really, even if it's a daughter.
So the real principle you only have to know, once we insert
the father here before the brother, it's going to become a very,
I think, a simple principle if you get the rule down, right?
Which is it goes to children, first sons, then daughters. If the
children, if people aren't alive, then you look for their descendants, okay?
So if there's no sons, you look for sons of descendants of
sons, whatever.
And after it goes to, if there's no sons and daughters and
no surviving heirs, children there, it goes to father, and then you
just repeat it. Okay? Then it goes to this person's sons and
daughters. And if not, his father. And if his father's already dead,
then it goes to his sons, right? And eventually, you're going to
have somebody's great-great, you know, grandchild who's still alive down here. You
know what I mean? It could wind up going to this guy's
third, you know, you know, great-great-great, you know, nephew twice removed, because
you kept on going up and across and down, and eventually, you're
going to get to some surviving child. Yes, Bobby.
I just was wondering, depending on ages, if actually the son is
no longer whatever, could it go to a grandson before it went
around the?
Yeah. If there's no sons and there are daughters, but there's a
surviving granddaughter, let's say of a granddaughter or son's daughter, it would
go to the son's daughter before it would go to the daughter.
It goes to surviving children of that stage before it goes to
the next stage. All right? So if let's say there's nobody surviving
here, but some great-great-great-great-great-grandfather had a brother who has a surviving great-great-great-great-grandchild,
eventually it'll get there because you keep on going up, you know,
up and then down, and if nobody's there, then up the next
level and down until finally somebody's going to be surviving down the
list.
Yes, Rabbi Dov. It's basically ממשמשין, Memashmishin, right? Yes.
Why ממשמשין? Memashmishin? ממשמשין Memashmishin is like you search out, I mean
it's a funny language. Yeah, like you search out, you know, the
next generation and then even if he's not alive, he's יורש בקבר.
Yoresh bakever. It's as if he inherited and then died and then
passed it on.
Does this make sense to you? This is an interesting, now, other
words, the answer to בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelafchad could have been, you
don't have to lose your inheritance. There's a lot of beautiful young
men in your tribe. You have a big tribe. Right, marry in
the tribe. That would be the answer, right? Except it's not necessity
that the land is going to be...
That's right. I mean, that's a power, is that they basically... Absolutely.
It's like, yeah, it's like they still saw themselves, you're right, in
the context of a patriarchy. The logical answer would have been, I'm
sorry you were born to this man, but this is not your
tribe, this is not your inheritance, your inheritance is going to be
your husband's inheritance. You know, and their claim that no, we are
still children of our father, you know, yes patriarchy, no patriarchy, we
deserve a portion in the land, right? That was definitely their חידוש.
Chidush. I mean, the חידוש Chidush that the תורה Torah responded to
that. Absolutely. Yes.
I was just going to ask, because when you said about העברת
נחלה Avarat Nachala and transferring to tribe, but they married within their...
Yes, so then that's what I said. That was the pushback. The
pushback was their uncles came and said, you know, hey, this is
going to leave the tribe. So then they modified it, fine, only
marry members of in your own tribe, but then חז"ל Chazal say,
and this was חז"ל's Chazal חידוש, Chidush, that that restriction was only
limited to that period of time, which is a very good thing
because, you know, could you imagine that restriction on marriage? That somebody
actually would be in a, like let's say nowadays, right? I mean,
you know, if somebody was a בת לוי, Bat Levi, right, or
whatever a בת, Bat, you know, whatever, how many tribes do we
have? If you were told you can't marry a member except it
has to be a, you know, of the same tribe, that actually
would work. You could only marry a member of the same tribe.
That actually wouldn't be a problem nowadays. But anyway, but חז"ל Chazal
said that restriction was, did not apply beyond the time of that
generation.
Okay, two very quick, two, did you have your question yet? Fine,
go ahead. Okay, and then we're moving on.
Yeah, so I'm saying is, I just wanted to point out, it's
interesting because, you know, we have other cases of like, you know,
we have שודא דדייני, Shuda deDayani, they think they say, oh, who
this guy would have wanted to give it to, who is he
closer, we have another view we don't do that at all. Right.
Meaning it could be somebody, you know, could be a brother he's
never even known like.
Right, well that's שארו, She'ero, defined by, defined by blood, not defined
by relationship, by,
by sentimental and emotional. Yes. Yes, no you haven't asked a question
yet. So you still have your...
So on the שארה כסותה ועונתה, She'era Kesuta VeOnata, the commentary that
it's family?
Yes, שאר She'er and the רמב"ן Ramban discusses, he says שאר She'er
means flesh. So שארה כסותה ועונתה, She'era Kesuta VeOnata, the רמב"ן Ramban
says that so if we read that שאר She'er means sustenance, it's
because it provides flesh to the body, food. But the רמב"ן Ramban
says that שאר She'er actually means
the man's flesh is his wife and she, or the woman's flesh
is her husband, and the רמב"ן Ramban says that actually he's referring
to, to marital intimacy, to marital relations.
That also comes back to...
But
okay, and we're going to also correct get to that issue of
wife as flesh later. So let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. Where
did Dan leave off? That was just up into... somebody's got to
tell me where we left off yesterday.
109.
Where, anybody?
אימא, Eima, אימא. Eima.
Second line, אימא שארו.
Eima
She'ero.
109.
Just pick up where you think is a good place.
Okay, fine.
Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara basically said was, so I'll just
say, so what the גמרא Gemara says is so we know the
father. Now, the גמרא Gemara says where do you sort of insert
the father? And what becomes fascinating about the גמרא, Gemara, which I
won't re-read inside, is once we're saying we follow this principle of
הקרוב אליו, hakvarov elav, then the גמרא Gemara says well then it's
all up for grabs. Then we don't have to read the פסוקים
pesukim literally. We're going to decide who is a closer relative. And
the גמרא Gemara actually suggested at the end of yesterday that if
we're following the principle of הקרוב אליו, hakvarov elav, let's say the
brother gets before the son because maybe a brother is a closer
relative because he does יבום yibbum than a son. So the גמרא
Gemara rejects that. It says no, the only reason the brother does
יבום yibbum is because there is no son or daughter. Obviously, son
or daughter is obviously a closer relative to a person than a
brother. And then a son also stands in his father's stead for
other הלכות, halakhot, for ליעוד liyud of a case of a female
slave or for cases of redeeming a sanctified field. So, but what's
up, the point is once we say הקרוב אליו hakvarov elav and
we're going to use it to insert father here, the גמרא Gemara
is saying now everything is up for grabs. We're going to figure
out the order, you know, we're willing to violate the simple sense
of the פסוקים, pesukim, so we're even going to suggest that a
brother can come before sons and it rejected that. So now we're
going to continue. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא אימא, ha eima,
so by the little אלף aleph on the top of קט עמוד
א. kuf tet amud aleph. אימא שארו זה האב. Eima she'ero ze
ha-av.
So okay fine, you said that שאר she'er means the father. But
now let's figure out where to put him. מלמד שאב קודם לבת.
Melamed she'av kodem le-bat. So once we are deciding where to put
father based on closeness, so let's put father between son and daughter,
right? Well, we could be biased towards the male patriarchy. Alright, so
if father-son is a tight relationship, so maybe if it doesn't work
down, it should work up before it goes to daughter. Okay, once
we're not going to be constrained by the פסוקים. pesukim. So יכול
יקדים לבן? yakhol yakdim le-ven? Maybe the father should even come before
the son? תלמוד לומר הקרוב, קרוב קרוב קודם. talmud lomar hakorov korov
korov kodem. No, קרוב קודם. karov kodem.
So therefore, no, no, no, there's no question that a son is
a closer relative than a father, right? The whole idea that a
son, you know, takes the place of the father once he deceases
and so on. So there's no question a son would come before,
a man's son would inherit him before his father. The question is
though, maybe a father comes before daughter. How do you know that
once it's all up for grabs a daughter comes sooner? No, כיון
דלענין יבום בן ובת כי הדדי נינהו לענין נחלה נמי בן ובת
כי הדדי נינהו. keivan de-le'inyan yibbum ben u-bat kiyadadi ninhu, le'inyan nachala
nami ben u-bat kiyadadi ninhu. No,
once we know that when a person dies that there's no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, it's not explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. The
פסוקים pesukim say, you know, איש... ish... what is it? כי ישבו
אחים יחדיו... איש ואחיו ומת אחד מהם ובן אין לו. Ki yeshvu
achim yachdav... ish ve-achiv u-met achad mehem u-ven ein lo. He doesn't
have a son. Again, this is a really, you know, big חידוש
chiddush of חז״ל, Chazal, because again, in the context of the patriarchy,
if you leave behind no son, you leave behind nobody to carry
on your name, to be part of that tribe, right? To be
part of the patriarchal household. And you could say that there's still
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum because the person left behind no
son. Okay, but חז״ל Chazal say no, even if he left behind
a daughter, that is still considered that he left behind progeny and
therefore there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum. So number one, it's,
we should appreciate that it's not פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim.
Okay, but number two is, so the גמרא Gemara says once we
have said that both the son or daughter exempts from a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, so that means that they are considered a
continuation of the person, even a daughter. Again, I want you to
appreciate the חידוש chiddush of this in the context of a patriarchy,
that we're saying that these are considered more, the daughter is considered
more of a direct continuation of the person, even though she's going
to marry a man possibly from another tribe, be part of another
household, the whole thing, and is considered closer to this man than
the father. Okay, so that is a very significant חידוש chiddush and
we should not minimize it, because we're not just talking about biological
closeness, right? We're talking about sort of like recognized, you know, family
as defined as how the family is structured, right? I mean, for
example, think about a sister through the mother, that's biologically closer than
a lot of these, but a sister through the mother is, or
a brother through the mother, right? Is completely irrelevant for laws of
inheritance. So it is not just a question of biological closeness, it's
a question of how you define family structure. So the idea that
a father would come before a daughter ignoring the פסוקים... pesukim... is
very logical and the גמרא Gemara actually says no, once we have
put a daughter here in the line of inheritance, she's actually considered
more close from the family structure, more of a continuation of this
man than is, than his father is. Yes, Michael?
Wait, I don't remember which words it comes from, but we have
other lines, שארו אל אשתו, she'ero el ishto, when introducing a wife
over there. אשתו כגופו. ishto kegufo.
Okay, we're going to, first time we'll get to wife. Okay, fine.
So alright, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, so תא שמע, ta
shma, so okay, כיון דענין יבום בנו ובתו כמותו דמינו לענין נחלה
נמי בנו ובתו כמותו דמינו. kivan de'inyan yibum beno u'vato k'vato dminu
l'inyan nachala nami beno u'vato k'vato dminu. Okay,
so again just to repeat, to appreciate that the fact that a
daughter exempts the brother from יבום yibum and is considered that the
man is still survives through his children, even his female children who
are not the tribe, not part of the household and so on,
and that that's also considered prior in his, in his continuation than
his own father, that is a very significant statement. Okay, so we
cannot insert the father before son, obviously, that's taken for granted, the
son is a continuation of the person. We can't insert him before
daughter, alright? That's because they are for יבום yibum purposes they're considered
that he still is surviving, he's still a continuation. So we're going
to insert him though before brother. And then the question is how
do you know, maybe he goes here, maybe he goes where he
naturally should go, maybe he doesn't get inserted here.
If he's no יבום yibum if there's a daughter then how does
the brother's name get...
That's my point, it doesn't really. I mean in terms of and
that's why it's a tremendous חידוש chiddush that the rabbis read it.
This daughter will now marry a man from another tribe, she'll be
part of another man's household, right? This person's household will effectively cease
to exist. The land will not be maintained, I mean it'll be
physically where it is, you can't move land, but it won't be
maintained under that person's estate, right? So it's a huge חידוש, chiddush,
right? And that's yes.
I just wonder why we never had a, a tradition of doing
a hyphenated name so she could have kept her family name hyphenated...
Yeah well, I don't know, they never, they didn't have last names
at all, you know until... בן-son-of... ben Yeah, exactly. Right, put a
hyphen on that hyphen.
Yeah, there you go.
Okay, they have מתגים, metegs, okay. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this:
okay, now, ואימא שארו זה האב מלמד שהאב קודם לאחי האב. ve'eima
she'ero ze ha'av melamed she'av kodem l'achei ha'av. Finally, fine! You want
to stick a father in here, stick him in where he belongs,
don't mis-rearrange the order of the פסוקים. psukim. Say he comes logically
before the father's brother. End of story, that's, that makes sense. Okay,
מלמד
שהאב קודם לאחי האב יכול יקדים לאחים? melamed she'av kodem l'achei ha'av,
yakhol yakdim l'achim? Maybe I might think he might come before the
brother, which is what we actually do say? תלמוד לומר הקרוב Talmud
lomar hakvarov, קרוב קרוב קודם. karov karov kodem. No, a brother is
closer to a father, so since a... and it makes sense that
a brother is closer to a father. A brother does יבום, yibum,
a brother is seen as the next, you know, generation to go
ahead and... Now horizontally. Now by the way, interesting to note about
this in terms of, of what do you call it, in terms
of יהודה ותמר. Yehuda veTamar. Right, there what was happening was, right,
that you know, the first son died, יהודה Yehuda said to the
brother go do יבום, yibum, whatever, the next one died, שלה Shelah
wasn't given over, תמר Tamar goes ahead and basically seduces יהודה. Yehuda.
So who wound up doing יבום? yibum? יהודה. Yehuda. The father. The
father wound up doing יבום yibum and the רמב"ן Ramban says it's
clear that in the ancient world there was already this practice of
יבום yibum and it wasn't restricted to the brother, it could actually
be if the, if there was brother wasn't doing it could be
another male relative.
So the fact that it's a possibility to think that a father
could do יבום yibum is not out of the way, but the
גמרא Gemara basically says, right, that, that no, at the end of
the day the father doesn't do יבום, yibum, the brother is clear,
is considered to be closer, right, than the father, the brother does
יבום, yibum, he's more connected than the father, that's the evidence that
he's closer. So if we're going by the principle of closer comes
first, why not, logic would be you keep the father there. Okay,
so that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא, lo, so the גמרא Gemara says as a classic גמרא Gemara
answer, אחי האב לא צריכי קרא אחי האב מכוח מאן קאתו מכוח
אב קאי מכוח אב.
achei ha'av lo tsrichi kra, achei ha'av mikoach man
ka'asu, mikoach av ka'i, mikoach av.
The brothers of the father, you didn't need a פסוק pasuk to
say the father came first, because the brothers of the father are
only getting it through their relationship to the father. So קאי אב
וירתי אחי האב? kai av ve'yartsi achei ha'av? Could I think that
the father would be alive and his brothers would get it and
not him? So the גמרא Gemara basically says you know what? You're
completely correct. Logically this is exactly where the father belongs. The father
belongs before the father's brother. But the point is if that were
the only thing that was, if that was the case that would
you would insert the father here, then the פסוק pasuk would not
have had to say לשארו הקרוב אליו, l'she'ero hakorov elav, insert the
father and go with the closest relationship first, because I wouldn't have
needed a פסוק pasuk to tell me to insert the father. I
could have figured that out by myself. It would have been obvious
that you would not give it to the father's brother if the
father was alive. So since without a special פסוק pasuk I would
have
known... he must be coming even earlier in the line of inheritance
so he's coming even earlier in the line of inheritance he must
be coming here he must be coming before the brother even though
logically the brother really is a closer relationship.
How do you read this line again? I'll read this line because
אבא מכוח מאי קאתי?
Abba mikoach mai ka'asi? אחי אבא מכוח מאי קאתו? Achei Abba mikoach
mai ka'asu? By the power of what would the father's brothers be
coming along inheriting? מכוח אבא. Mikoach Abba. Through the father. קאי אבא
כי ירתי אחי אבא? Kai Abba ki yarsi achei Abba? Do you
think the father could be alive and his brothers would inherit rather
than him? No of course if the father is alive he inherits
before his brothers. So you don't need a פסוק posuk to tell
you that.
You got it?
Yeah I got it. You know what confuses me? What confuses me
is קאי Kai with the י yud at the end plural?
No I don't know. No okay. I don't know I can't answer
that. Okay anyway what I'm going to actually do here just so
that this actually is also topographically in order I'm just going to
change this a little so we can sort of go around like
this.
One two like this. Okay so what we've just done is we've
inserted the father here. So by inserting the father here okay this
would be the father I mean now you can't sort of do
it like this but now he gets before the brothers. Okay so
we insert the father and he gets before the brothers because to
put the father
yeah make it all nice and goes so it goes in order
okay.
Okay so
so what we so so logically of course you would have said
son daughter then brother then father then father's brother. But then you
wouldn't have needed a פסוק posuk you would have known that father
came before father's brother. So therefore since there's a פסוק posuk to
tell you insert the father we're going to insert the father right
over here and the father is going to come before and the
father is going to come before the brothers. Okay even though logically
the brothers are a closer relationship. Alright everybody get what we're doing?
Alright let's move on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay והאי תנא מייתי לה מהכא. Ve'hai tanna maysei lah mehacha. That's
where this תנא tanna learns it from. שארו She'ero inserts father and
therefore he had to be inserted in some place I wouldn't have
imagined him to be inserted he would have obviously have gone there.
Since it's inserting him I'm going to insert him before brothers. Okay
that's where we that's from that פסוק. posuk. But the following תנא
tanna learns it from a different פסוק posuk that the father inherits
and where does and he inherits before the brothers. דתניא Detanya we
taught in a ברייתא. braita. זו דרש רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Zo
darash Rabbi Yishmael berabi Yosei. The following דרשה drasha is you know
expounded Rabbi Yishmael berabi Yosei. איש כי ימות ובן אין לו והעברתם
את נחלתו לבתו. Ish ki yamut uven ein lo veha'avartem es nachalato
levito. Oh I'm sorry. והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. Veha'avartem es nachalato levito.
Excuse me. So again we're going to focus on the word והעברתם.
veha'avartem. You should you should transfer over. So what's that language of
transfer over to the daughter? So we're going to read it in
the following way that it's going to be given to the daughter
prior it's going to be taken away from a person that we
would have thought would have been more entitled to it. And we're
going to transfer it take it away from the person who logically
would have been next in the line of inheritance and rather give
it to the daughter. So who would we have thought would have
logically been next after the sons? And the תורה Torah is saying
don't give it to that logically next person take it away from
them because that's actually what the תורה Torah was doing. It had
a line of inheritance and it said don't give it to the
next person after the sons who would have gotten otherwise take it
away from that person and give it to the daughters. So who
is that person that would have well no grandsons would get. Okay
so who is that person? So again what we would say is
it would have been brothers. Don't give it to the brothers give
it to the daughters. Daughters come before brothers. But we're going to
say we're going to insert the idea father here. And we're going
to say without the פסוקים psukim I would have said sons and
then father but the תורה Torah is saying don't give it to
the father give it to the daughters. But implicitly by reading the
פסוק posuk that way we're sort of reading our assumptions into the
פסוקים psukim and then reading them back. Okay by reading the פסוק
posuk that way don't give it to the father give it to
the daughters first we're saying ah so the father comes next after
the sons and daughters. So let's read it.
איש כי ימות ובן אין
לו והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו.
Ish ki yamut uven
ein
lo veha'avartem es nachalato levito. Okay so במקום בת אתה מעביר נחלה
מן האב. Bemakom bas atah ma'avir nachalah min ha'av. When there's a
daughter
you take it away from the father and you give it to
the daughter. ואי אתה מעביר נחלה מן האב במקום אחים. V'ei atah
ma'avir nachalah min ha'av bemakom achim. But if there's brothers brothers don't
come before the father. Now there's nothing in the פסוק posuk We
are completely reading our assumptions into the פסוק, pasuk, okay? And we
are saying that take it away from when there's no sons, take
it away from the rightful person whatever, the person who otherwise would
have been entitled and give it to the daughters meaning take it
away from the father and give it to the daughters. But if
there is a father, you won't take it away from the brothers
and give it to the father. Okay, if you're gonna tell me
the פסוקים psukim there again, there's nothing in the פסוק pasuk that
says that the father is here, right? It's just we're reading that
into the פסוקים. psukim. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute,
so the גמרא Gemara sort of asks that
question ואימא ve'eima I could read the פסוק pasuk otherwise במקום בת
אתה מעביר נחלה מן האחים bemakom bat ata ma'avir nachala min ha'achim
when there's a daughter, meaning the father maybe doesn't go here, okay,
when there's a daughter the next person would have been the brothers,
when there's a daughter you take it away from the brothers and
you give it to the daughter, maybe the father doesn't intervene. Okay,
ואי אתה מעביר נחלה מן האב אפילו במקום בת, ve'ee atta ma'avir
nachala min ha'av afilu bemakom bat, but maybe now where would you
put the father? So you could have said when there's no sons
and daughters take it away from the brother, but the father you
could have put him up here. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
if I want to, if I'm reading the פסוקים psukim how I
want to, I could read the father even earlier, I could say
that maybe the father, what is it, ואי אתה מעביר נחלה מן
האב אפילו במקום בת, ve'ee atta ma'avir nachala min ha'av afilu bemakom
bat, but I could say that the father would come before the
daughters, right? You don't know here, there's nowhere it says the father,
you're reading it into the פסוק. pasuk. So why do you read
into the פסוק pasuk take it away from the father and give
to the daughters and putting the father here, maybe the פסוקים psukim
should be read take it away from the brothers and give to
the daughters and put the father here, put the father even before
the daughters? How do you know not to do that? So
the גמרא Gemara says אם כן לא נכתב רחמנא והעברתם, im ken
lo niktav rachmana veha'avartem,
then the פסוק pasuk should not say that you transfer it away.
Now, what does that mean, what is the word והעברתם veha'avartem sort
of telling you that you can't read it that way? So it's
not exactly clear what that response is, I want to just remind
myself how תוספות Tosafot explains that it should have said ונתתם. venatatem.
Right.
So
because if the father was coming before the daughter, if the order
was sons and then father and then daughter, then you would not,
the daughter wouldn't have been taking it away from somebody that was
more entitled since the next person after the sons would have been
a male. Okay, again we're going again with the assumptions of patriarchy,
that's why בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelafchad is such a חידוש. chiddush. So
והעברתם veha'avartem means you're taking it away from a male heir and
giving it to the daughters, that's part of the חידוש. chiddush. If
at point after the sons you're giving it to a father, so
if the next person in line is a male heir,
then you wouldn't be emphasizing that the daughters are taking it away,
intervening and taking it away from the next male heir because it
would have been sons and then fathers and then daughter. But if
it's sons and then daughters, that the next person after the sons
is a daughter and they're getting next rather than a male heir
once there's no sons, then that's the פסוק והעברתם, pasuk veha'avartem, that
that's the חידוש chiddush that you're sort of violate those basic rules
of the patriarchy and you're taking away. Okay, so the bottom line
is here, it's a complicated דרשה, drasha, really not clear in the
פסוקים, psukim, but what the גמרא Gemara is basically saying is one
way or another, we are saying that we are going to assume
that the פסוקים psukim are telling me that the father comes before
the brothers. Okay, maybe I'll even, so it's going to be one
A and one B and then the father is going to be
number two. Okay, and that's actually what we're going to say, that
whichever פסוקים psukim you learn it out from, whether it's שארו she'eiro
that inserts the father, and to insert him in some way that's
a חידוש, chiddush, we're going to say he comes before the brothers,
or whether it's this פסוק והעברתם pasuk veha'avartem which basically says that
after the sons somebody else should have been getting it, some other
male heir should have been getting it, and rather than that male
heir it's the daughters, and we're going to assume that that other
person who should have been getting it was the father, and therefore
when there are no daughters the next person it'll go to will
be the father. Yes, Rabbi Dov?
I'm not holding
onto the beginning of this when you said האב קודם לבת, ha'av
kodem labat, but it's not true because the בת קודמת לאב, bat
kodemet la'av, how do we read that line again?
Where, I don't know which line you're going on.
מלמד שהאב קודם לבת, melamed she'av kodem labat, יכול יקדים לבן. yachol
yakdim laben.
That was a הוה אמינא. hava amina. Oh, fine. Okay, yeah, alright.
Yes, Bobby.
Are we just assuming, I probably covered this when I wasn't here,
that the wife doesn't inherit because she could marry out of the
tribe?
We haven't got there yet. yet to the wife, we will get
to the wife, okay? But yes, meaning there's no provision for the
wife. The only provision is for
daughters. Once you've included daughters here, I want to point this out,
this is very important, that has a huge ripple effect. That means
if there are no sons, but the son has a son or
the son has a daughter, the daughter will also inherit, right, the
granddaughter will inherit. If there's no brothers, but the brother has a
son, then that son will inherit. If the brother has no sons,
but the brother has a daughter, that daughter so this including daughters,
although they're after sons, okay, but including daughters actually then has an
application to the entire chart. All right? But we did not, we
never included wives. The only female that can inherit is through, is
through, you know, father, you know, but through a wife, a lateral
type of like a non-blood relationship, you know, cannot inherit. Okay, we
haven't yet said that, but it's not in the פסוקים psukim and
we're going... okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: So now we've got father where we want him
in the chart. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולמאן דנפיק ליה מוהעברתם.
u'leman d'nafik ley m'v'ha'avartem. If you're learning the father from the פסוק
pasuk of you transferred away and give it to the daughter, right,
that's the second דרשה, drasha, האי שארו מאי עביד ליה, hai she'eiro
mai avid ley, what does he do with the פסוק pasuk שארו
she'eiro which the first דרשה drasha used to put the father in
the chart? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, מיבעיא ליה לכדתניא, mibaya
ley l'chidi'tanya, like we taught in a ברייתא. baraita. And here you
go, Bobby, and Michael who's not here anymore, שארו זו אשתו. she'eiro
zo ishto. שארו she'eiro means his wife. Now, if you said, ונתתם
את נחלתו לשארו, u'ntatem et nachalato l'she'eiro,
to his wife הקרובה אליו, ha'kerova elav, then what would it mean?
That who inherits who? If the word is give it to his
שארו she'eiro and we say שארו she'eiro means אשתו, ishto, then you
would've said when a man dies, give it to his wife. Okay,
but we're going to say no. What it means is, he inherits
his wife. He doesn't bequeath to his wife. It's not 'give it
to his שארו', she'eiro but give what is his שארו she'eiro לו,
lo, okay? ונתתם, u'ntatem, we are going to read it, ונתתם לשארו
u'ntatem l'she'eiro as ונתתם שארו לו. u'ntatem she'eiro lo. Give
what is his wife's to him.
ונתתם מ u'ntatem mi
something like that.
So we are putting wife in that פסוק, pasuk, but we are
putting wife in the פסוק pasuk to say that he inherits from
his wife. Now, by the way, I want to say something about
this, okay? Is the inheritance of, does the fact that a man
inherits his wife דאורייתא d'ora'ita or דרבנן d'rabbanan is a debate of
the ראשונים. rishonim. רמב"ם Rambam holds that it's only דרבנן, d'rabbanan, this
דרשה drasha is an אסמכתא. asmachta. A man really does not inherit
his wife because you need a blood relationship to inherit. This is
very related to this week's פרשה. parsha. This week's פרשה parsha talks
about כהן kohen can become טמא. tamei. And the פסוק pasuk says
כהן kohen becomes טמא. tamei. It says, לא... lo... it says, כי
אם לשארו
הקרוב אליו.
ki im
l'she'eiro ha'kerov elav. Notice the same פסוק: pasuk: שארו הקרוב אליו. she'eiro
ha'kerov elav. כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו, ki im l'she'eiro ha'kerov elav,
who's שארו הקרוב אליו? she'eiro ha'kerov elav? לאמו ולאביו ולבנו ולבתו ולאחיו
ולאחותו,
l'imo, u'l'aviv, u'l'vno, u'l'vito,
u'l'achiv, u'l'achoto,
right? ולאחיו... u'l'achiv...
ולאחותו
הבתולה
הקרובה אליו, u'l'achoto habetula hakerova elav, ולאחותו הבתולה, u'l'achoto habetula, right? לה
יטמא. la yitama.
Okay? Okay, so who's not in that פסוק? pasuk?
Doesn't say בתו? bito?
Yes, לאמו ולאביו ולבנו ולבתו. l'imo, l'aviv, u'l'vno, u'l'vito. Thank you, ולבתו.
u'l'vito. That, that... now you got... what does that mean?
Okay, that's a Freudian there. Anyway, I left it out like בנות
צלפחד. Bnot Tzelafchad. לאמו ולאביו ולבנו ולבתו ולאחיו ולאחותו ולבנו ולבתו. l'imo,
l'aviv, u'l'vno, u'l'vito, l'achiv, u'l'achoto, u'l'vno, u'l'vito. Oh, I put in ולאחותו,
l'achoto, I should've put in ולבתו. l'vito. ולבתו ולאחיו. u'l'vito, u'l'achiv. Okay.
אשתו ishto is not there. No. Okay. So what חז"ל Chazal say
is, who's שארו הקרובה אליו? she'eiro ha'kerova elav? Who is his flesh
that is closest to him? That's his wife. And they read wife
into the פסוק pasuk with the word שארו. she'eiro. But I want
to tell you, פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim might be saying
the exact opposite. Because what does the next פסוק pasuk say? לא
יטמא
בעל בעמיו
להחלו.
lo yitama ba'al b'amav
l'heychalo. What does that mean? What's בעל בעמיו? ba'al b'amav? The פשט
pshat of that פסוק pasuk might be saying a husband should not
become טמא tamei to his wife, that would defile him, and he
can only become טמא tamei to his blood relatives. But, you'll see
רש"י, Rashi, okay, but the Rabbis read שארו הקרוב אליו she'eiro ha'kerov
elav is his wife, but רמב"ם Rambam says that's a דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
Now how could a כהן kohen become טמא tamei to his wife
if it's only a דין דרבנן? din d'rabbanan? So רמב"ם Rambam says
they made her like a מת מצווה. meit mitzvah. They said nobody
else is allowed to bury this man's wife, so therefore it's a
מת מצווה. meit mitzvah. If he's the only person available to bury
her, then a כהן kohen could become טמא tamei to a מת
מצווה. meit mitzvah. But the רמב"ם Rambam consistently says that the connection
of husband to wife to inherit and to become טמא tamei is
rabbinic. Most ראשונים Rishonim assume that it's דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, that חז"ל Chazal
are reading this, that that's really פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim.
Okay, so a husband comes טמא tamei and he inherits his wife,
but it doesn't work the other way, right? It's still a patriarchy
here, so it still goes to the male other than introducing the
daughters by בנות צלפחד, Bnos Tzelofchod, it's not going to pass to
a female, but it will pass from the wife to the husband
and that's the this פסוק possuk of שארה הקרוב אליו. She'eira Hakarov
Eilav. One last point about this, which is the idea of a
wife as flesh, because that's what שארה she'eira means, so it was
mentioned before by the פסוק possuk that it says by the wife,
it says what does it say by the wife, it says right
the obligations of a husband owes his
wife is right שארה כסותה ועונתה. she'eira ksusa ve'onasa.
So what does flesh—שארה she'eira means flesh. So רמב"ן Ramban says some
say it means sustenance like providing you know the meat on the
bones, but the רמב"ן Ramban says no, it means their conjugal relations
becoming one flesh, and the רמב"ן Ramban well he says it's different
aspects of עונה. onah. And the רמב"ן Ramban says this goes back
ultimately to the פסוק possuk of
והיו לבשר אחד. vehayu lebasar echad. So if they're one flesh then
that then the wife becomes שאר, she'eir, and if she becomes שאר
she'er that allows חז"ל Chazal to read it into that it's the
closest flesh right? So that's a very powerful idea that there's no
biological relationship, right, between husband and wife, no actual blood relationship, but
once והיו לבשר אחד, vehayu lebasar echad, we are now reading in
that his flesh that is closest closest to him is his wife.
Yes, and maybe even closest to him. He's בשר אחד basar echad
with his wife, he's not בשר אחד basar echad with his father
or his mother or his son or his daughter. Right, so it's
a very powerful read of חז"ל Chazal to read wife into the
כהן Kohen and into the inheritance.
Yes, I do it does resonate with me also this parallelism between
אבילות aveilus like death טומאה tumah
and נחלה nachala through the continuity and continuation and it's a bloodline,
but what bothers me is the הלכה halacha in אבילות aveilus should
be that if a child God forbid predeceases the parents, parent should
also be in אבילות aveilus for a year.
Okay, so the year issue is not because of the depth of
אבילות, aveilus, the year for a parent is because of כיבוד אב
ואם. kibbud av va'eim. So actual—so that's—so that's why—know everybody's deeply troubled
with that, you know, why is it that, you know, or when
a spouse dies the גמרא Gemara says אין איש מת אלא לאשתו
ואין אשה מתה אלא לבעלה, ein ish meis ela le'ishto ve'ein isha
meisa ela leba'alah,
that the person who experiences it most closely is the spouse, so
why is the אבילות aveilus shorter than for a parent, which is
the more natural order of things and so on. So the basic
point is for the parent it's a year because of כיבוד אב
ואם, kibbud av va'eim, not because of the depth of the אבילות.
aveilus. Yes.
How is the wife protected when the husband dies?
That's what the כתובה kesuba is about. The כתובה kesuba provides for
her a lump sum and she's allowed to continue living in the—you
know—and being provided for from the estate in terms of lodging and
food and so on. That's what the כתובה kesuba is about is
exactly that. Yes.
Does the priest become one flesh is it related to the idea
that השם Hashem originally
created—yeah well that's where it comes from, that they started as one
flesh and then they were separated, so then they come back together.
That's exactly the context of that פסוק. possuk. Okay so now let's
continue.
Okay, מלמד שהבעל יורש את אשתו, melamed she'haba'al yoresh es ishto, ולמאן
דנפיק ליה משארו—so ulemanda nifik lei mishe'eiro if שארו she'eiro is coming
to tell you father, האי והעברתם מאי עביד ליה? hai ve'ha'avartem mai
avid lei? What do you do with והעברתם? ve'ha'avartem?
Okay right the transfer. We use העברתא ha'avarta to say like I
don't know to put the father in here, but if you learn
father elsewhere what do you do והעברתם? ve'ha'avartem? So this is what
I told you earlier. So מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, miba'ei lei lekhiditanya, like
we turned in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אומר Rebbi omer בכולה נאמר
בהן נתינה, bekulah ne'emar bahen nesina, by all the other relatives it
says you shall give the inheritance, והכא נאמר בהן העברה, vehachan ne'emar
bahen ha'avara, you shall pass it over or transfer maybe is a
better word, you shall transfer it to the daughter, שאין לך שמעביר
נחלה משבט לשבט אלא בת, she'ein lekha shema'avir nachala mishevet leshevet ela
bas,
because when you give because when it goes to the daughter that
will transfer it away to a different tribe. הואיל ובנה ובעלה יורשין
אותה, ho'il uvinah uva'alah yorshin osah,
because her husband and her son will inherit from her. Okay, her
son because the son inherits, and her husband so you know רשב"ם
Rashbam points out that this is also a way you could learn
in that a husband inherits his wife since it says and actually
I think this could be the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim,
and it's clear from the fact that the uncles come and complain.
The uncles come and complain and they say these בנות צלפחד Bnos
Tzelofchod they'll marry other men and the inheritance will go to a
different tribe. Well what's implicit in those פסוקים? psukim? That when you
marry a man a woman marries a man and she dies her
husband inherits her, right? That's clear from that's the complaint of the
brother—of the uncles right. So that's what רבי Rebbi is saying. If
it says you transfer to a daughter the word transfer means once
you're giving it to a daughter it's—it could leave the tribe. How
does it leave the tribe? It leaves the tribe if Because if
a woman dies, either her son, who now is from a different
tribe because her husband's a different tribe, so it either goes to
her son or her husband inherits her. So implicit in the word
והעברתם v’ha’avartem is the idea that it goes to another tribe, and
implicit in that is that a son and husband inherits from a
woman. Okay, and that's that trait, that aspect of it. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, וממאי דשארה זו האב. u'mimai
deshe'erah zo ha'av. Now going back to the דרשא drasha that שארה
she'erah inserts the father. How do you know that refers to the
father? דכתיב שאר אביך היא, dich'tiv she'er avicha hi, who, he, right,
שאר אביך she'er avicha what is it, he I think, it's what
is it, אשת אביך שאר אביך היא. eshet avicha she'er avicha hi.
Okay, who, he, he, שאר אביך היא. she'er avicha hi. וממאי, u'mimai,
okay, so it says שאר אביך. she'er avicha. Now of course the
irony is שאר אביך she'er avicha doesn't mean your father is your
שאר, she'er, it means your
father's wife is your father's שאר. she'er. Oh by the way, that's
a פסוק pasuk that uses שאר she'er referring to a husband-wife relationship.
Anyway, אימא שארה זו האם eima she'erah zo ha'em דכתיב שאר אמך
היא dich'tiv she'er imecha hi which also refers to the mother's relationship
to somebody anyway, whatever, but anyway it uses the word שאר she'er
with mother. אמר רבא אמר קרא amar Rava amar kra now here
is super important principle that we've been assuming all along and here
it's said black and white. How do you know that if there's
no son and daughter, the same way you use שארה she'erah to
insert father, let's insert mother? Let's say a man's mother can inherit
him. So you know how you know that that's not going to
happen? Because we still have a patriarchy. We still, okay? So אמר
קרא amar kra because the פסוק pasuk says ממשפחתו וירש אותה mimeshpachto
veyarash otah from the same family. The inheritance stays within the family.
Okay, and here is here is the important rule: משפחת אב קרויה
משפחה משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה. mishpachat av kriya mishpacha mishpachat em
eina kriya mishpacha. And that's I mean, that is, you know, obviously
patriarchy nowadays has negative connotations, but patriarchy is a descriptive word. It
means that the family structure is defined through the father. Okay, it
goes father-son, that defines the family structure. And that is exactly that
line is the description of patriarchy. משפחת אב קרויה משפחה משפחת אם
אינה קרויה משפחה. mishpachat av kriya mishpacha mishpachat em eina kriya mishpacha.
If you are related to somebody only through your mother, you're not
from the same family. We have a shared mother and different fathers?
I'm from Reuven's family and you're from Shimon's family. The fact that
we have a shared mother is a biologically interesting, biologically we're
half-siblings or whatever, but we are not from the same family. Families
are defined by the men, not by the women. That is the
definition of patriarchy.
Yes, and that makes some statement about the discrepancy between this fact
of patriarchy and status being coming through the mother and not...
Oh, yeah, that's always the question. The Jewish status comes through the
mother or status...
right, yes, it's worth noting. I don't have anything profound to say
about that, but yes, Jewishness passes through the mother is definitely a
big חידוש chiddush given that idea that tribal and family identity is
defined by the father.
שאר אביך היא שאר אמך, she'er avicha hi she'er imecha,
how does that prove that it's the שאר she'er is... it doesn't.
It's just because it's juxtaposed. It's very bizarre how it's using that
פסוק. pasuk. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says now how do you
know that? That a family is only defined through the father.
משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה. mishpachat em eina kriya mishpacha. דכתיב למשפחתם
לבית אבותם dich'tiv lemishpachtam leveit avotam through their families, their father's household.
That definitely is פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay. So says
by the way, so people who add mother's names sometimes to like
כתובה ketubah and other things, which I do, like, you know, ראובן
בן שמעון ורחל. Reuven ben Shimon veRachel. So I know there are
some people who want to be like really progressive and even reverse
the order, ראובן בן רחל ושמעון. Reuven ben Rachel veShimon. But that
I don't think you can do because fundamentally, you know, the fundamental
we're still fundamentally it's a patriarchy. You know, that's the tradition, that's
what it is. So the basic identity is still father-son or daughter-father,
what a son-father or daughter-father, you know, so that still remains the
basic structure. משפחת אב קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av kriya mishpacha, yeah. Why
do
we use the mother for מי שברך? mi shebeirach?
So the reason given is that that's to be like עורר רחמים,
orer rachamim, you know, from God to talk about like, you know,
compassion, motherly love and so on, right, gave birth, right, so would
be, right. Okay.
Now
ומשפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה? u'mishpachat em eina kriya mishpacha? You mean
to tell me we would never identify somebody through the household of
the mother, the family of the mother? Again, not that he's not
biologically related, but what family are you a part of, right? You're
telling me that it's not the mother? והכתיב ויהי נער מבית לחם,
vehach'tiv vayehi naar mibeit lechem, this is the story of פסל מיכה.
Pesel Micha. מיכה Micha basically took all of this silver and he
fashioned it into an idol and then he got this and he
made whatever, it sounded like it sounds almost like... that he was
not worshipping another God, but using this idol as a way of
worshipping God, and he had and he used these things. Anyway, he
had this person who was a לוי, Levi, the story says, who
came to be his כהן, Kohen, his priest for this idol, for
this house of worship, and then the story continues. So here's the
story about this לוי Levi that came to be part of this
house of worship
or that he persuaded to join to join his like temple. Okay,
so it says: ויהי נער מבית לחם יהודה, Vayehi Naar MiBeit Lechem
Yehuda, there was a youth from Beit Lechem, יהודה, Yehuda, which is
in
Judea, ממשפחת יהודה, mimishpachat Yehuda, from the family of יהודה, Yehuda, והוא
לוי, vehu Levi, and he was a לוי. Levi. So, what is
he? A לוי Levi or a יהודה? Yehuda? So, והוא גר שם,
vehu gar sham, and he was living there. So, הגופא קשיא. hagufa
kashya. אמרת והוא לוי, Amart vehu Levi, you said he's a לוי.
Levi. אמרת מלוי אתי, Amart miLevi ati, you see he descends from
לוי. Levi. ממשפחת יהודה, mimishpachat Yehuda, then it says from the family
of יהודה. Yehuda. אמרת מיהודה אתי, Amart miYehuda ati, he comes from
יהודה. Yehuda. אלא לאו דאבוה מלוי ואימיה מיהודה? Ela lav de'avuha miLevi
ve'imei miYehuda? It must be his father's a לוי, Levi, because still
his identity is still לוי, Levi, right? There's no question that the
father's household is the primary one, but even though you say fundamentally
he's a לוי, Levi, you still say he comes from the family
of יהודה. Yehuda. You can still recognize the mother's family as a
type of a grouping. It's not completely invisible. Okay,
so דאבוה מלוי ואימיה מיהודה, de'avuha miLevi ve'imei miYehuda, וקרי ליה ממשפחת
יהודה. vekari lei mimishpachat Yehuda. So even though again his primary tribal
identity is clearly father, you still see that he's part of his
mother's family; that's not invisible, that's still a type of a family
grouping. אמר רבא בר רב חנא: Amar Rava bar Rav Chana: לא,
lo, גברא דשמיה לוי, gavra dishmeih Levi, that man's name was לוי.
Levi. Okay? והוא לוי, vehu Levi, that was his name. It could
have
said והוא ראובן. vehu Reuven. The גמרא Gemara says, so now it's
a פשט. pshat. The גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי היינו דקאמר מיכה,
ei hachi hainu dekamar Micha, if his name just happened to be
לוי, Levi, מיכה Micha was very happy when he was able to
persuade him to be a priest. And מיכה Micha said: עתה ידעתי,
ata yadati, now I know, כי ייטיב ה' לי, ki yeitiv Hashem
li, God will do good for me, כי היה לי הלוי לכהן,
ki haya li haLevi lekohen, I was able to get a לוי
Levi to be my priest in this temple. He was a temple
to God with an idol, but it was a temple to God.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so just his name was לוי? Levi?
If he was a לוי, Levi, you understand why he was happy.
Right, exactly, so the גמרא Gemara says: אין הכי נמי גברא דשמיה
לוי, in hachi nami gavra dishmeih Levi, yes, somebody whose name was
לוי Levi happens to be my priest. That's also a good סימן.
siman. הלוי, haLevi, what was I telling- anyway. Okay, so
obviously it's not פשט. pshat. פשט pshat is that he was a
לוי. Levi. So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי לוי שמו? vechi Levi
shemo? One minute. You can't tell me his name was לוי. Levi.
והלא יהונתן שמו, vehalo Yehonatan shemo, his name was יהונתן, Yehonatan, שנאמר,
shenemar, because then it says by the end of the story is
that then the Danites came and they basically stole the פסל pesel
and they stole the priest, they persuaded the priest to come with
them and they conquered some land and then they set up a
whole temple of this in Dan with this guy and his descendants
as priests. So the end of that
פסוק pasuk is: ויהונתן בן גרשום בן מנשה, v'Yehonatan ben Gershom ben
Menashe, הוא ובניו היו כהנים לשבט הדני. hu uvanav hayu kohanim leshevet
haDani. They were the priests in this temple for the שבט shevet
of Dan. So it sounds like his name was יהונתן בן גרשום
בן מנשה. Yehonatan ben Gershom ben Menashe. Okay, so you can't say
his name was לוי. Levi. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said back, ולטעמיך, u'letaameich, according to you, וכי בן מנשה הוא? vechi
ben Menashe hu? He wasn't really the son of מנשה. Menashe. והלא
בן משה הוא, vehalo ben Moshe hu, because it says גרשום בן
מנשה, Gershom ben Menashe, we know that משה Moshe had a son
גרשום. Gershom. So the גמרא Gemara actually says the נ nun is
actually in a way extra. It really is גרשום בן משה. Gershom
ben Moshe. Maybe it wanted to hide the fact that here this
priest to this idol- it was an idol to God but still
priest to an idol was משה's Moshe grandson. So it was hiding
it, so it says- so he's really משה's- Moshe he was really
משה's Moshe grandson: דכתיב בני משה גרשום ואליעזר. dechtiv bnei Moshe Gershom
ve'Eliezer. So why does it call him יהונתן בן גרשום בן מנשה?
Yehonatan ben Gershom ben Menashe? אלא מתוך שעשה מעשה מנשה, ela mitoch
she'asa maaseh Menashe, which is a little what do you call it
anachronistic, because מנשה Menashe wasn't for many generations, but because he acted
like the מנשה, Menashe, this later king who was such an idolater,
תלאו הכתוב במנשה, tala'o hakatuv beMenashe, it made it as if מנשה
Menashe was his grandfather. Okay, now how's that relevant for us? Bottom
line is his name wasn't לוי. Levi. He clearly was a לוי.
Levi. So you see though, and it still calls him from the
family of יהודה. Yehuda. So אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן
יוחאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, I'm sorry, הכא
נמי מתוך שעשה מעשה מנשה דאתי מיהודה תלאו הכתוב ביהודה. hacha nami
mitoch she'asa maaseh Menashe de'ati miYehuda tala'o hakatuv biYehuda. Ah, but מנשה
Menashe also was from יהודה. Yehuda. So when it says he was
from the family of יהודה, Yehuda, we don't mean that you can
attribute somebody's family based on their mother. It means he was he
was like those יהודה-ites Yehuda that are idolaters. Of course it's completely
anachronistic because מנשה Menashe was many, many generations later. Okay, but the
way we're getting out of it is we have to concede that
he was truly a לוי Levi because his name was יהונתן. Yehonatan.
Okay, but so how- it's a לוי, Levi, he's called from the
family of יהודה. Yehuda. It doesn't literally mean the family of יהודה.
Yehuda. It means he was he was like
one of those יהודה-ites. Yehuda who know many, many generations later will
be idolaters, he too was an idolater. So it's a pretty weak
way of getting out of it. פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Psukim
is definitely there is still a family can be recognized through the
mother, but the גמרא Gemara is rejecting that. The only recognized family
grouping is through the father. Yes?
Independent of the hermeneutics, the content of it is, this מדרש Midrash
is suggesting that משה רבנו's Moshe Rabbeinu grandson was an idolater?
Yes, and
the גמרא's Gemara going to continue with that point tomorrow. It's not
going to let up on that point. Okay, so the last line
I want to say though is once we have established, okay, once
we have established, this is important, last point everybody pay attention again,
introducing the daughters in a patriarchy is a huge חידוש, Chiddush, right?
Because that's normally you would say that's not recognized as part of
the family, daughters are part of a different family. So the גמרא
Gemara is asking, what I want to sort of summarize the point
of the גמרא, Gemara, if we're going to recognize that daughters can
be part of a family even within the context of a patriarchy
to inherit, maybe mothers can as well. And maybe if there's no
father, let it, let's start recognizing the family on the mother's side,
let's start recognizing the mother. So basically says like no. Okay, this
person, the only family he's a part of is his father's family,
he's not part of his mother's family. So so he cannot give
to his mother. His family is his father's. Okay, he can give
to his daughter because still the father is determining. So the father
can give to the daughter. Okay, daughter is still his child, but
he can't give to his mother because his mother is not part
of the family. The family is defined through the males. Okay, so
it's an interesting balance here between introducing something that disrupts the patriarchal
structure, but not completely disrupting it. It's still not going to go
to a mother because fundamentally the family grouping is defined by, and
even the mother isn't even like a secondary family. Why don't we
say he's primarily his father's family, but he's also his mother's family?
And that's, that would make sense. Let her be a secondary family,
so you can pass after the father, and we reject that as
well. His only family grouping is through the father. All right, so
that's an interesting pushback to this introduction of daughters is we're not
going to let mother be here even in some type of a
secondary type of a role. All right, we will continue with...